# John Joseph Valletta

68 Glasney Place Penryn TR10 8LN

Mobile: 0784722721 jiyalletta@gmail.com

#### **Profile**

A data scientist who spent the past decade working on a wide spectrum of datasets, ranging from intricate mechanical systems to complex human diseases. By combining expertise from the fields of control engineering, machine learning and statistical modelling, I have developed data analytics methodologies to extract knowledge from complex and noisy datasets and visualise them.

## **Education and Qualifications**

# University of Southampton, UK

2007 - 2011

Ph.D.

• Thesis: Dynamic Modelling of the Effect of Habitual Physical Activity on Glycaemic Control and the Microvasculature in People with Type 1 Diabetes

# University of Sheffield, UK

2006 - 2007

M.Sc. Control Systems Engineering (Distinction)

• Project: Model Structure Selection and Validation for Linear and Nonlinear Dynamic Models

# University of Malta, Malta

2001 - 2005

B.Eng (hons.) Electrical Engineering (First Class)

• Project: Adaptive Fuzzy Control of an Inverted Pendulum System

## **Employment History**

### University of Exeter, UK

2014 - present

Medical Research Council (MRC) Research Fellow

• Integrating multi-omics and immuno-epidemiology data for biomarker discovery in malaria

### McLaren F1 Racing Ltd., UK

2011 - 2013

Aerodynamic Applications Engineer

• Developed data analytics frameworks to translate noisy wind tunnel and track data into knowledge about air flow structures to direct the aerodynamic design process of F1 cars

# University of Southampton, UK

2010 - 2011

PhD Plus Research Associate (now renamed EPSRC Doctoral Prize)

• Decomposing microvascular blood flow signals to identify potential biomarkers with links to cardiovascular risk factors and endothelial dysfunction

#### Hyperdrive Technologies, UK

Aug 2010 - Oct 2010

Research Engineer (Internship)

• In-depth market research into hybrid powertrain to support the business plan of a start-up

#### University of Southampton, UK

2007 - 2010

Teaching Assistant

Automotive Quality Engineer (based in Detroit, USA)

# **Teaching Experience**

## Workshops

- "Life beyond the P value from elementary to advanced data analysis", BioMalPar XIV: Biology and Pathology of the Malaria Parasite coference, Heidelberg, Germany, May 2018
- "Python for scientific research", University of Exeter, June 2017
- "Introduction to machine learning for the life sciences", University of Exeter, June 2015

## Undergraduate modules

• Scientific computing, Ecology and Evolution of Disease, Engineering Principles, Electrical Systems

## Supervision

- "Text mining of Twitter data", Mathematical Sciences Project, Jakub Kryczka, 2018-19
- "Gaussian Processes for short time-series modelling", Mathematical Sciences Project, Alex Holt, 2018-19
- "The Effects of Physical Activity on Capillary Blood Glucose Concentration in Type 1 Diabetes", Undergraduate Independent Research Project, Suzanne Shuttleworth, 2009

## Awards and Grants

- **2017** University of Exeter researcher-led initiative award fund (£1,500) to run the workshop "Python for scientific research"
- **2015** University of Exeter researcher-led initiative award fund (£1,000) to run the workshop "Introduction to machine learning for the life sciences"
- 2011 Blue Riband Poster Prize at the 26th Meeting of the European Society for Microcirculation
- 2011 Conference Attendance Fund (£500) (University of Southampton) to present at the annual European Association for the Study of Diabetes conference in Lisbon, Portugal
- 2010 2011 EPSRC Ph.D. Plus Fellowship (now renamed to EPSRC Doctoral Prize)
- 2010 Conference Attendance Fund (£500) (University of Southampton) to present at the annual European Association for the Study of Diabetes conference in Stockholm, Sweden
- 2009 International Travel Grant (£500) (Royal Academy of Engineering) to present at the annual IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology conference in Minnesota, USA
- 2007 2010 Ph.D. Studentship (University of Southampton)
- 2007 Laverick-Webster-Hewitt Prize for outstanding academic performance (University of Sheffield)
- 2006 2007 EPSRC M.Sc. Studentship
- 2005 Best Academic Performance Prize (University of Malta)

#### **Publications**

- **J.J.** Valletta<sup>1</sup>, Y. Bediako<sup>2</sup>, R. Adams<sup>2</sup>, A. Reid<sup>2</sup>, F.M. Ndungu<sup>2</sup> et al., "Repeated clinical malaria episodes associated with modification of the immune system in children", submitted for review
- D.E. Gates, J.J. Valletta, C. Bonneaud and M. Recker, "Quantitative host resistance drives the evolution of increased virulence in an emerging pathogen", to appear in *Journal of Evolutionary Biology*, 2018
- T. Holding, J.J. Valletta and M. Recker, "Multi-scale immune selection and the transmission-diversity feedback in antigenically diverse pathogen systems", to appear in *The American Naturalist*, 2018
- **J.J. Valletta** and M. Recker, "Identification of immune signatures predictive of clinical protection from malaria", *PLoS Computational Biology*, 13(10):e1005812, 2017
- **J.J. Valletta**, C. Torney, M. Kings, A. Thornton and J. Madden, "Applications of machine learning in animal behaviour studies", *Animal Behaviour*, 124:203-220, 2017
- S.M. Ewings, S.K. Sahu, J.J. Valletta, C.D. Byrne and A.J. Chipperfield, "A Bayesian network for modelling blood glucose concentration and exercise in Type 1 diabetes", Statistical Methods in Medical Research, 24(3):342-372, 2015
- **J.J. Valletta**, A.J. Chipperfield, G.F. Clough and C.D. Byrne, "Daily energy expenditure, cardiorespiratory fitness and glycaemic control in people with Type 1 diabetes", *PLoS ONE* 9(5): e97534, 2014
- **J.J. Valletta**, A.J. Chipperfield, G.F. Clough and C.D. Byrne, "Metabolic regulation during constant moderate physical exertion in extreme conditions in Type 1 diabetes," *Diabetic Medicine* 29(6):822-826, 2012
- **J.J. Valletta**, A.J. Chipperfield and C.D. Byrne, "Gaussian process modelling of blood glucose response to free-living physical activity data in people with Type 1 diabetes," in *Proceedings of the 31st IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Annual Conference*, (EMBS 09), Minnesota, USA, pp. 4913-4916, 2009.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>1</sup>ioint first authors